Soha Tariq

st.sohatariq@gmail.com | (240) 899-8167 | Washington D.C., DC

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/soha-tariq-5226143b/ | GitHub: https://github.com/SohaT7

Portfolio: https://sohat7.github.io/Portfolio/

Summary

Data Analyst/Scientist with 2+ years of experience in data analysis, data modeling and data visualization with sales data, healthcare data, school district data, scholars data, economic data, earthquake and weather data, cryptocurrencies and credit risk data, and stocks data. Looking for a **Data Analyst/Data Scientist** position to solve business problems with Python, Numpy, Pandas, R, SQL, Tableau, and Machine Learning, in order to generate actionable insights.

Skills: Python (Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Scikit-learn, Tensorflow libraries), Structured Query Language (SQL), Tableau, Microsoft Excel, Visual Basic Application (VBA), R, PostgreSQL, SQLAlchemy (ORM), MongoDB, HTML5, CSS, JavaScript ES6+, RESTful APIs, Flask, BeautifulSoup, Amazon Web Services (AWS), Google Cloud Platform (GCP) - BigQuery and Vertex AI, Hadoop, version control GitHub, Jupyter notebook, Google Colab notebook. Exploratory Data Analysis (EDA), ETL pipeline, web scraping, data modeling, data cleansing, data analysis, data visualization, database management (queries), agile methodology, machine learning.

Professional Certifications

Data Analytics

Columbia Engineering Bootcamp

June 2022

Professional Experience

Freelance

Remote

Data Analyst

March 2022 - December 2022

- Conducted data analysis (including Exploratory Data Analysis (EDA), ETL pipeline formation, pivot tables and pivot charts) and data visualizations on multiple datasets, using Python, SQL, R, Excel, Tableau, and Javascript.
- Developed machine learning and logistic regression models to help predict future trends in the data, using Python and R.

Columbia University Data Analytics Bootcamp

New York, NY

December 2021 - June 2022

Data Analyst

- Constructed web applications and interactive maps, generated in-depth data visualizations (graphs, charts, tables), and conducted web scraping using a variety of data-driven programming languages including Python, R, SQL, and JavaScript.
- Used advanced SQL, Python libraries, and Mongo to combine multiple datasets into more comprehensive databases.
- Employed statistical analysis to model, predict, and forecast trends using tools in Excel, Python, R, and Hadoop.
- Created Python-based scripts to automate the clean up, restructuring, and rendering of large, heterogeneous datasets.
- Interacted with RESTful APIs and parsed data in JSON format.
- Developed Machine Learning models using Python, for cryptocurrency data, credit risk data, restaurant data, and healthcare data.

Success Academy Bronx, NY

- Conducted regular data collection, data cleaning, data analysis, data querying, and visualization on scholars' data, in Microsoft Excel and SQL, to identify the need for academic intervention and specialized services from the Committee on Special Education (CSE).
- Improved the tracking and monitoring process design by introducing advanced data analytics which made early detection of at-risk students more efficient by about 25%.
- Conducted effective meetings and built stakeholder relationships with NYC Department of Education (DOE) to finalize academic plans for students in need.

Lahore University of Management Sciences (LUMS)

Lahore, Pakistan

Data Research Assistant

June 2017 - March 2018; September 2013 - December 2013

- Built relationships with the local communities to assess issues faced when engaging in the politics of infrastructure and in intergenerational occupational mobility.
- Led a team of 9 in data collection from 8,000 households in 15 low-income neighborhoods.
- Conducted mapping of the neighborhoods made data collection faster by about 50%.
- Developed and maintained a database, conducted data cleansing, data mining, preliminary data and statistical analysis, and data visualization, in Microsoft Excel, R and STATA.

Innovative Development Strategies (IDS)

Lahore, Pakistan

Data Analytics Intern

June 2014 - August 2014

- Conducted data collection (questionnaires, interviews, and focus groups) in 7 localities, followed by data cleaning, analysis, and data visualization of the aggregate data in Excel.
- Prepared a report and presented the results to government stakeholders on the issues faced by the Internally Displaced People (IDPs), with recommendations to alleviate those issues.

Projects

Amazon Product Reviews Analysis | GitHub: https://github.com/SohaT7/Amazon_Vine_Analysis
Big data analysis to determine if there is a positivity bias in product reviews written by Amazon Vine members (paid versus non-paid members).

Tools: Amazon Web Services (AWS), SQL, PySpark, Python (Pandas library), pgAdmin

Movies ETL Database | GitHub: https://github.com/SohaT7/Movies-ETL

Creates an automated ETL (Extract, Transform, Load) pipeline that extracts data on movies and their ratings from multiple data sources, to then transform (data cleansing, formatting, applying functions) and load the data into a movies database.

• Tools: Python (Pandas and Numpy library), PostgreSQL, and SQL

Credit Risk Analysis | GitHub: https://github.com/SohaT7/Credit Risk Analysis

Supervised machine learning models built and evaluated to predict credit loan risk. Resampling and ensemble techniques applied to the logistic regression classifier models.

• Tools: Scikit-learn, Imbalanced-learn, Pandas, and NumPy libraries in Python.

Cryptocurrencies Analysis | GitHub: https://github.com/SohaT7/Cryptocurrencies

Unsupervised machine learning algorithms (PCA dimensionality reduction and K-means clustering algorithm) report on tradable cryptocurrencies and create a classification system for them.

• Tools: Scikit-learn, Pandas, Plotly, and hvPlot in Python.

Additional Experience

University of Virginia . Teaching Assistant	August 2019 - December 2020
United We Reach . Curriculum Writer	November 2018 - June 2019
AIESEC in Lahore & Kenya . Project Manager; Marketing Advisor	September 2011 - August 2014
Education	
Masters of Arts, Anthropology . University of Virginia	August 2019 - December 2020